<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise, very comfortable for all those Christians that be troubled and disquieted in theyr consciences with the sight of their owne infirmities wherein is shevved hovv such may in their owne selues finde whereby to assure them of their free election, effectuall vocation, and iustification.</title>
            <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12708)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise, very comfortable for all those Christians that be troubled and disquieted in theyr consciences with the sight of their owne infirmities wherein is shevved hovv such may in their owne selues finde whereby to assure them of their free election, effectuall vocation, and iustification.</title>
                  <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Bynneman for] Ralph Newbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Sparke.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Part 2, "A brief and short catechisme", has a separate title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>C1r catchword: "nesse"; E2r catchword: "likelye"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; quires A-D only filmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:1"/>
            <p>¶ A ſhort Treatiſe, very comfortable for all thoſe Chriſtians that be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and diſquieted in theyr conſciences with the ſight of their owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities:</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhevved hovv ſuch may in their owne ſelues finde whereby to aſſure them of <hi>their free election, effectuall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>verſe</hi> 17.</bibl>
               <p>Euery good tree bringeth foorth good fruite, and a corrupt tree bringeth foorth euill fruite.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 18.</bibl>
               <p>A good tree can not bring foorth euill fruite, neither can a corrupt tree bring foorth good fruite.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London by Ralph Newbery. Anno Domini.</hi> 1580.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſaluation in Chriſt IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen theſe few leaues were writ at the firſt (Chriſtian Reader) it was not my meaning thus by print to haue made them common, for they were writte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the requeſt of a perticular man, for the comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of his troubled ſoule, but ſince one writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten coppy hath begot ſo many, and made me haue ſo many ſuters for moe, the number of afflicted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences being in theſe dayes ſo many as I know they be, and they that haue had the reading heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of already, reporting and confeſsing vnto me that thereby they haue bin much comforted, though I know that it was not nor is not penned ſo exactly, nor yet the matter dealt in ſo ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tially as things in theſe dayes to be publiſhed had neede to be, yet I haue ſuffered my ſelfe by the importunitie of the godly that haue requeſted euen this at my hands to be ouerread, and ſo to publiſh it I hope for the benefite of all thoſe that ſhall reade it: for this I am ſure of. I haue ſo layd downe comforts for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the broken hearted Chriſtian, that withall I haue I hope taken all occaſion from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and godleſſe, of taking cauſe to be ſure by any thing heere ſet downe, which I take to bee very neceſſary to be regarded in ſuch preatiſes and
<pb facs="tcp:2584:3"/>diſcourſes: wherefore be the Reader hereof a right and true Chriſtian, or a carnall and counterfeyte Goſpeller, he may in this ſhort and briefe tracte find that which may be profitable for him: if he be of the later ſort, then here ſhal he learne that where true iuſtification in deede is, there is alſo ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and that therefore he deceyues himſelfe in preſuming of the former, hauing neuer had any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntance with the later: and if he be of the firſt ſort, be he weake, or ſtrong in faith, heere ſhall he find both matter to leade him on in his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and to rayſe him vp in his weakeneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take it vnto thee Chriſtian Reader, and learne to make thy profite of it according to thy hearte, and a ſalue of it according to thy ſore. That thou mayeſt thus do, I beſeech the Lord to direct thee in reading of it with his ſpirit, and hauing done I pray thee recompence my good will in commending me vnto God in thy heartie Prayers agayne. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Christ Ieſus Thomas Sparke Archdeacon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:3"/>
            <head>How a man ſhall be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his ovvne conſcience of his election, effectuall vocation, and iuſtification.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is certayne, he that is deſirous to knowe whether he be one whome God hath elected, and according to the ſame his election effectually called and iuſtifyed, he is to conſider whether he be yet ſanctified or no, and thereby to iudge of his election, vocation, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: for where this ſanctification is founde, there the partye that hath it in poſſeſſion, is aſſured that he is the choſen childe of God effectuallie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto that eſtate, and in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus iuſtified, and ſo in the ende ſure to bée glorifyed, as it maye well and euidentelye appeare bothe by the iudgemente of Peter, and alſo of Paule, whereof, the firſte exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to the particular braunches of
<pb facs="tcp:2584:4"/>ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as namely to knowledge, temperance, patience, godlyneſſe, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe, and loue, addeth thys as a reaſon to adde force vnto his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Bréethren giue dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to make your calling and election ſure, for if you do theſe things, ye ſhal neuer fal. <hi>2.</hi> Pet. <hi>1.</hi> verſe <hi>5.</hi> and the other Rom. <hi>8.</hi> as he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth thoſe that be in Chriſt of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, vocation, and iuſtification, yea and in the end, of their aſſured glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying, there is no condemnation to thoſe that be in Chriſt Ieſus, ſo he in the words immediatly following, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth how to know thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in Chriſt, and ſo conſequently thoſe that be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, called, iuſtified, and in the end to be glorifyed, ſaying Which walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, which ſame leſſon Chriſt our ſauiour hathe taught vs, Math. <hi>7.</hi> verſe. <hi>18.</hi> ſaying: A good trée cannot bring forth had fruite, nor yet a had trée can bring forth good fruite, and alſo Ioh. <hi>15.</hi> verſe. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi> where he ſaith, as the branch can not beare fruite of it ſelfe except it abide in the vine, no more
<pb facs="tcp:2584:4"/>can yée, except yée abide in me, I am the vine, yée are the branches, he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in me, and I in him, the ſame brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth much fruite. Héereby I ſay then it is euident, as ſéeking the cauſe why we are elected, called, iuſtified, and finally ſhall be glorified, we find the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe to be Chriſt Ieſus, and therfore are enforced to acknowledge hym the only dore into the ſhéepefold Ioh. <hi>10.</hi> the way, the truth, and the life Iohn. <hi>14.</hi> and his name to be the only name whereby commeth ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Act. <hi>4.</hi> ſo we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled being aſked who be elected, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, iuſtified, and to be glorified, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, they onely that ioyne vertue to their faith, that walke not after fleſhe, but after the ſpirite, and ſo being good trées of the Lordes planting in Chriſt Ieſus Eſa. <hi>61.</hi> and Iohn. <hi>13.</hi> bring foorth the fruites of righteouſneſſe, that is, thoſe only that be ſanctified, for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word accompteth ſanctified, in whome the ſanctifying ſpirit ſheweth it ſelfe to dwell by the right fruites of the ſpirit, wrought in them, which all conſiſt in
<pb facs="tcp:2584:5"/>ſacrificing, crucifying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ciſing, mortifying, killing, and burying of the old man, and in putting on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ing, renuing, and ſtrengthning of the new man, which repreſenteth the ymage of God in holyneſſe and righteouſneſſe, Epheſi. <hi>4.</hi> If therefore to our eternall comfort we would be certifyed of thys poynte, whether we be of the number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaued, let vs not ſéeke to be reſolued thereof by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into conſideration of Gods ſecret purpoſe, but let vs in the reuelation of Ieſus Chriſt vnto vs, and in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured tokens and mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of thoſe whome God in him hath purpoſed to ſaue, learne to know and vnderſtande what Gods purpoſe is towardes vs. For as it is written by Paule in the firſte Chapter vnto the Epheſians, and the thirde verſe, In hym it is, in whome the heauenlye father hathe bleſſed vs in all manner of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſings in heauenly things, according as he had choſen vs in him before the ſoundations of the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:2584:5"/>were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayde, that we ſhoulde be holy and withoute blame before him tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Loue. In déede God in deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe to vs, and in bringing vs to full poſſeſſion of hys bleſſings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth by theſe ſteppes, béeyng of nature good and louyng towardes mankinde, thoughe in mutable manne there was found cauſe why hée ſhould altogither bée ſhuffe from taking any benefite by thys loue of God towards him, yée, God being of nature immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſeuered in his loue towards ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fréely of his own good wil purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſaluation of vs men in his ſon Chriſt Ieſus, and electeth and predecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateth vs to be ſaued through and for hym, béefore the foundations of the worlde, and therefore in time by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe reuealeth thys hys purpoſe, and when the fulneſſe of Tyme was come, ſente hym, in whome, by whome, thoroughe whome, and for whoſe ſake hys purpoſe ſhoulde ſtande ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and thoſe, whoſe ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſte thus promiſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="tcp:2584:6"/>from euerlaſtyng hée purpoſed thoſe by his worde and ſpirite, in hys good time he maketh effectuallye to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how able and willing he is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in hys ſonne Chriſte Ieſus to iuſtify: and there ſtayeth not, but by the ſame meanes he worketh faith in theyr hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whereby they catch holde of Chriſt, and ſo in hym of full iuſtification. Thus when hée hath made them trées of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of his own planting in Chriſt, then he ſo purgeth and trimmeth them, that they may bring forthe muche fruite to his glorie in this life, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come he may make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partakers of his owne glorie: ſo that God of his own good will purpoſeth to ſane, or electeth whome he liſte, and thoſe he calleth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he liſteth, and them iuſtifieth and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth here, that hée maye in hys good time glorifie elſewhere. Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But nowe, if wée would know Gods purpoſe of vs, wée haue to beginne at the loweſt or laſte effecte of hys good purpoſe towardes vs, and thereby by degrées to aſcende to fynde oute what
<pb facs="tcp:2584:6"/>hys abſolute decrée is to doe wyth vs: that is, lette vs conſider whether we be ſanctified or no, if not, it is in vaine ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bragge of Iuſtification, Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Election, or to preſume of Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: vntil this be founde in vs, wée can haue no aſſurance of anye of theſe: but when this is once ſounde in vs, then foraſmuch as none be ſanctified, whom hée hath not iuſtified, and none iuſtified, whome he hath not both effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in tyme, and elected before al times, and none euer was partaker of all theſe but in the ende alſo there was glorified, we may thereby aſſure our ſelues, that we are alreadye iuſtified and therefore called, called and therefore elected, and conſequently ſuche as ſhall bée glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, as all is not gold that gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: ſo all is not Sanctification or true holineſſe that ſéemeth ſo to be. For, we reade in the <hi>29.</hi> Chapiter of Eſay of ſuch as drewe nigh to God with their lippes, and yet were farre from hym in their hearts: and Eſay <hi>28.</hi> God in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing
<pb facs="tcp:2584:7"/>a people, in whome he founde nothing but ſin and tranſgreſſion to bée cryed out of, yet ſaith thus of them, yet they ſéeke me dayly, and woulde knowe my wayes, euen as a nation that dydde righteouſly, and hadde not forſaken the ſtatutes of their God: in theſe then ther ſéemed to be holines, and yet was none: So in the Scribes &amp; Phariſies in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes tyme in the eyes and iudgementes of men, there ſéemed to be notable ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification or holineſſe of life, inſomuch, that in that reſpecte Chriſte compareth them to ſuche as made cleane the vtter ſyde of the Cuppe, and of the Platter, and to painted tombes whyche appeare beautiful outward. And yet there he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth manye he any woes againſte them, &amp; pronounceth them Hypocrites, Serpents, and generation of Vipers, Math. <hi>23.</hi> And therefore Chriſte hathe tolde vs, Math. <hi>5.</hi> verſe <hi>20.</hi> Excepte our righteouſneſſe excéede the righteouſnes of the Scribes &amp; Phariſies, we ſhal not enter into the kingdome of Heauen: &amp; hath alſo warned vs, that we be not like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither in giuing of almes, praying,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:7"/>nor faſting, Math. <hi>6.</hi> The Aungell of the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had a name y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he liued &amp; yet was dead, Reuel. <hi>3.</hi> deſcribing the wickednes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt times, he ſaith, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal haue a ſhew of godlineſſe, out haue denyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power therof. Theſe places the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euidently do teach vs to take héed that we do not flatter our ſelues, &amp; think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfore al is wel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, bicauſe outwardly we appere to men ſanctified &amp; righteous, for we ſée here, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſéeming but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> being righteous y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God as a marke &amp; true token of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal enter into Heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how voide are they of any true hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is neither fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d holines in déed, neither yet ſo muche as an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew therof, being men which liue ſo wickedly, that al men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance &amp; familiarity with them, ſée and beholde their prophane and wicked liues. But nowe let theſe alone, let vs take this profite by this leſſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs vpon to be righteous in déede, if we be deſirous hereby to reape any aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of our election and iuſtification.
<pb facs="tcp:2584:8"/>And hereby let vs take occaſion to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (leaſt we be deceiued in accompting our ſelues truely righteous, when wée are not) what thynges be neceſſarye to true righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>For the vnderſtandyng whereof, if we reſorte vnto the Scriptures of God, thereby ſhall wée learne, that true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and perfect, is a ceaſing from all the ſinnes condemned in the lawe in heart, worde, déede, and countenaunce, and an embracing all the vertues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the ſame, in hearte, worde, déede, and countenaunce. And further, thereby ſhall wée plainely learne, that he that woulde walke in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before the Lorde, he hath to regard two principal things, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter namelye, that hée exerciſe hym ſelfe in, and the maner howe to doe it: For, if either bothe of theſe, or one of theſe be neglected, the labor is loſt. The matter of a good worke is that onely which is warranted lawfull to be done, eyther expreſſely or by ſound collection out of the Canonicall Scriptures, for it
<pb facs="tcp:2584:8"/>is written yée ſhall put nothing vnto the word that I command you, neyther ſhall you take aught therefro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deu. <hi>4.2.</hi> and good reaſon is there why we ſhould obey this precept, for the holy Scripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to reproue, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be abſolute, being made perfect vnto al good works, <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi> verſe. <hi>16.17.</hi> and therfore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily Chriſt reiecteth all ſuch workes or poyntes of his worſhip which haue no ground out of ſhe word, ſaying, Mat. <hi>15.</hi> in vayne they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines mens preceptes, thereby telling the Phariſtes though they were neuer ſo paynefull and deuoute in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing their owne traditions, yet hée would make no accompt of their ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but as of vayne and loſt laboure. Vpon this ground Paule Coloſſ. <hi>2.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth al works that haue no better warrant than the commaundementes and doctrines of men, thoughe there bée in them neuer ſo muche ſhewe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:9"/>&amp; humbleneſſe of mind as vaine &amp; fooliſh, verſe, <hi>20.</hi> &amp;c. By this rule all the wil worſhipping &amp; wil-workes in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, lacking allowance from the word, are proued ſuch as neuer coulde be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of godlineſſe. But when thou haſt &amp; ſuche regarde to the matter thou takeſt in hand, be it tending to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, or practiſe of vertue, that thou arte aſſured out of the word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou oughteſt to be occupied therein, yet then haſt thou not done: for vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> do the ſame thing in right maner, it léeſeth the power of a good work. It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denyed, but that almes and prayer to God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, &amp; therfore good matter of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but yet as it is euident, Math. <hi>6.</hi> though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scribes &amp; Phariſtes did bothe theſe, yet were they not accompted good works then, bicauſe they were not done in right maner. The Lord in the firſt of Eſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, that he regarded not their ſacrifices &amp; burnt off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes he ſignifieth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he lothed them, &amp; counted their labor therein beſtowed vaine, &amp; their incenſe abhomination, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:2584:9"/>yet it is well knowen, that then ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were matters allowed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ded of God, yet bicauſe when they were done, they were not done as they oughte to haue béene, therefore the Lorde thus deſpyſeth the doyng therof. Wherfore it is not ynough, as the dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe practiſe vnder Antichriſte cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>les to beléeue, to giue almes, to faſte, to pray, to vſe the Sacraments, &amp; neuer to care howe and in what ſorte to doe theſe thinges: for we ſée, that thoughe theſe things be done neuer ſo much and neuer ſo oſt, yet, if they be not done in right maner, they are reiected of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord as vain &amp; as abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in his ſight. Now in their maner of doing theſe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are to be regarded. Firſt, that they pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éede (I mean al our actions) from a heart puriſted by faith. For as <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>2.</hi> verſe <hi>5.</hi> we be taught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the end, ſum, or perfection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole law, is Loue: ſo are we told, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it commeth out of a pure hart, &amp; of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, ſaying, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true chriſtil loue indéed is not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d growing where ther is no pure hearte, neyther
<pb facs="tcp:2584:10"/>can there be a pure heart where is not a good conſcience, neither yet can this g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od conſcience be where there is abſent an vnſayned Faith: but where this vnſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned faith is, that is, where a ful and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led perſuaſion or aſſuraunce of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is throughe Jeſu Chriſt alone wrought in the heart by the holy Ghoſte, thereis a good conſcience, bicauſe, being iuſtified by Faith, we haue peace with God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our Lord Jeſus Chriſt Rom. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; ſo ther is alſo a pure hart, for it is faiths propertie to purify y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart, Act. <hi>15.</hi> verſe. <hi>9.</hi> And therfore is it writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that by ſaith <hi>Abel</hi> offred a better ſacrifice than Caine Heb. <hi>11.</hi> verſe <hi>4.</hi> For if there hadde bin faith in <hi>Caine</hi> as in <hi>Abell,</hi> his ſacrifice had bin as well accepted as <hi>Abels,</hi> but euen for lack of this, it was not. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we lacke faith in God, when we go about a good matter, we léeſe our labor, for it is impoſſible to pleaſe God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out faith, Heb. <hi>2.</hi> verſ. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; therfore eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gay &amp; glorious works of Turks, Iewes, Atheiſts, Heretikes, &amp; Papiſts, are proued to be no good works at all in
<pb facs="tcp:2584:10"/>the ſight of god, bicauſe they proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as are deſtitute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Chriſtian faith. Secondly, we muſt take héed, that our workes be done in humilitie and lowlineſſe of mind, taking our ſelues to be bound, as indéed we are, to doe more than we do or can do, yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being ready to ſay &amp; think indéed, as Chriſt hath taught vs, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue done al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to do (whiche is impoſſible for vs to do, Act. <hi>15.</hi> Rom. <hi>8.</hi>) that we bée but unprofitable ſeruants. Luk. <hi>17.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that this Humilitie muſte be of meaſure in vs, that it cauſe vs alwayes to ſuſpect our own weakneſſe &amp; infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo there may be founde in vs a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trembling &amp; feare to offend oure good God, in omitting the leaſt neceſſary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of a good work, as we be tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte Phil. <hi>2.</hi> verſe. <hi>12.</hi> in theſe wordes: Make an end of your ſaluation in ſeare &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling. That this humilitie &amp; lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind is neceſſarily to be ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exercizing our ſelues in good matters, Chriſt hath plainly taught vs Luk. <hi>18</hi> in the parable of the Phariſie &amp; Publican:
<pb facs="tcp:2584:11"/>there it appeares, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Phariſie had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed himſelfe in good matters, both in abſtayning from outwarde fins, and in doing of good and lawfull things, &amp; yet bicauſe, when he had done, he lackte hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, &amp; therwith was puft vp to think that God was therfore indebted to him, he mard al, &amp; loſt al his labor. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al merit-mongers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that by their works they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued Heauen, for al their bragging of works more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ynough to iuf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues withal, are by Chriſte ſent home vniuſtified, yea not ſo much as once rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned &amp; accompted amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workers of any iuſt &amp; holy work. Thirdly, leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhold think that in teaching vs to be thus lowly minded when we goe about a good work, we be taught therein vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſtruſt or diſpaire, that god wil at any time regard our good workes, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we muſt learne of the worde, to ioyne hope with our humilitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the one preſerueth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſte in our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, ſo the other may kéep vs from vtter diſpairing that God wil reward them:
<pb facs="tcp:2584:11"/>But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this hope may be found in vs, we muſt not ſéek to grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any kind of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe in our ſelues, for when we looke into our ſelues, &amp; conſider our works, as they come from vs in great imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we find &amp; ſee our ſelues to tremble &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ar, being ready al of vs to ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Eſay c <hi>4.</hi> at our righteouſnes is but as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thye clouts, but we muſt reſorte to Chriſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as in him we our ſelues are iuſtified, ſo for his ſake theſe pore fruites of oures might be accepted. To teach vs thus to doe, Peter hath ſaide vnto vs, <hi>1.</hi> Epiſtle Chap. <hi>2.</hi> to whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e come as vnto a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtone diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lowed of men, but choſen of God and pretidus, and be made a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall houſe, a holy prieſthoode to offer vppe ſpirituall ſacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt. He knew ſul wel, that to encourage Chriſtians to exerciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in godlines, which he termes here the offering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſpiritual ſacri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it was nece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ry to teach th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us, that though when they had done, they ſhould find no cauſe in their own works wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe why they ſhoulde be accepted of God, that yet acceptable they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:2584:12"/>be in Chriſt Ieſus, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus yet he mighte teache them to doe good workes in hope that their labour ſhoulde be acceptable in Chriſte, and for his ſake, the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and imperfections of their workes being conered through his good meanes. Fourthelye, bée the matter neuer ſo godly, that we doe, that yet it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to take it in hande, and to procéede therein of loue, and by loue, Paule hath notably taughte vs <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> ſaying: Thoughe I ſpeake wyth the tongues of men and Aungels, and haue not Loue, I am as a ſounding braſſe or a tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling Cimball, and thoughe I had the gifte of Prophecie, and knew all ſecrets and all knowledge: yea, if I hadde all Faith, ſo that I coulde remoue Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and hadde not Loue, I were nothyng: and thoughe I ſéede the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re with all my goodes, and thoughe I gyue my body that I be br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned, and haue not Loue, it profiteth me nothing: By loue, I meane that two ſolde loue towardes God and man, it muſte not be the loue of our ſelues, loue of the worlde, or loue
<pb facs="tcp:2584:12"/>of aduantage that muſt ſet vs on work, but loue in déede vnfained by to wardes God, bicauſe he hathe loued vs ſo fréely and effectually in Chriſte. And this loue we can no way ſhewe towards him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than in giuing of oure ſelues fréely and wholy, hartily and continually to obey his laws and commaundements: For, he that ſaith he loueth him, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not his commaundements, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leth with him: The hyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of loue workes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eringly and ſoone is weary, but where loue ſetteth a worke, there the worke is done dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, and faithfully, &amp; that not for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye appeare, that we giue our ſelues is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>iueſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen of loue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un that is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe it ſelfe, let vs buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet oure ſelues ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe it their fully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our grudging for God lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h a thée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giuer, diligently, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>lly, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſed is he that doeth the worke of the Lord negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and let vs perſeuer and continue in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, without fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing or giuing
<pb facs="tcp:2584:13"/>ouer, for bleſſed is he that perſeuereth to the end, &amp; he that putteth his hend is the plough &amp; looketh backe, is not méete for the kingdome of Heauen. Finally, &amp; laſt of al, that nothing be lacking, learn we out of the <hi>6.</hi> of Math. to take héeds, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſéeke not vain glorie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, the praiſe and glory at mans hand for our wel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but let our principal end be the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, as Chriſte hathe taught vs, Math. <hi>5.</hi> ſaying: Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſée youre good works, and glorifie your heuenly father which is in heauen: and aming thus at this marke by the way, we ſhal there by edifie our neighbors by our good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, and aſſure our ſelues to our great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of our election, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e two excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ends, vſes, &amp; comu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dities y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riſe to vs by our good works. Thus exerciſing our ſelues, and wraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iug according to the meaſure of oure faith, euery day to be leſſe ſinfull &amp; more righteous, though that perfect righteouſneſſe that the law requyreth, be not founde in vs by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of oure weakeneſſe, yet wée age
<pb facs="tcp:2584:13"/>counted in the ſighte of GOD ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified holy, &amp; acceptable in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and ſo ſealed vp to the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. Paul without al doubt was in ſtate of Iuſtification, and a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate or newe borne, and therefore ſuche a one as had put off the olde man, and putte on the newe, when he wrote his Epiſtle to the Romaynes: and yet there in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eauenth Chapiter it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that hée ſounde in hymſelfe when hée hadde done what he could, ſin dwelling, inſomuch that he confeſſeth, that he didde not the good thing that hée would, but the euil thing that he wolde not, that did he, and that he felt a lawe in his members rebelling e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayuſt the law of his minde, leading him captiue vnto the lawe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue, and therefore he cryeth out of himſelfe ô wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliner me from thys body of ſinne, and death. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Corinthians. <hi>12.</hi> hée confeſſeth, that he hadde a pricke in his fleſhe whyche hée calleth the Meſſenger of Sathan that bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>itted him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the whych his faith he
<pb facs="tcp:2584:14"/>prayed thrice that it might depart from him, but he ſayeth anſwere was made him that Gods grace was ſufficient for him, and that his power was made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect through weakeneſſe, whereby God taught him that ſo it is, and will be eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the holyeſt of vs all, that there wil remayne in vs alwayes whiles we liue ſome reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of old Adain is humble vs to wreſtle and fight againſt: this is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be obſerued, leaſt that any vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion of the former do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rine ſhoulde gather againſt himſelfe, that foraſmuch as he ſéeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n &amp; infirmities in himſelf, that therefore he is not ſanctified and ſo void of any aſſurance of his election and iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for though Paul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it thus with himſelfe, yet bycauſe in the inner man he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound a wreſtling &amp; a ſtriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g againſt theſe ſinnes in his fleſh, he aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe that he is one whom God had ſo certainly purpoſed to ſaue for his Chriſtes ſake, that in his owne perſon, &amp; in the perſons of all other in the ſame caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was, he ſaith, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded that neyther death nor life, nor Angels,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:14"/>nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor deapth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is abte to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus oure Lord Rom. <hi>8.</hi> ſo that let not <hi>Peccatum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abitans</hi> ſinne dwelling in the fleſh, in the which we know with Paule that no good thing dwelleth Rom. <hi>7.</hi> diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs, ſo that we be able to ſay truly with the ſame Paule, we delite in the Lawe of God concerning the inner man. In déede we muſt accompt that Paule hath ſayd vnto the regeuerate, Let not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> raigue in your mortall bodyes, that yée ſhoulde obey it in the luſtes thereof. Rom. <hi>6.12.</hi> and thereby gather that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we be ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fied and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerate in déede, that then ſinne is put from his reigne or kingdome in vs: but their the muſt vnderſtand, that there is greate diſterene betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te <hi>Peccatum regu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>catum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that is, betwéet ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e reiguing in vs, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then is in his reigne and king<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when he hath the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb facs="tcp:2584:15"/>of man redy to yéeld him their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary or willing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, taking de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in doing of him ſeruice, in whiche eſtate ſin is in vs till we be regenerate &amp; haue put on Chriſt, wheby his ſpirita diſpoſſeſſeth ſin of his kingdom: howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it then til death come, in ſome meaſure it will be founde in man, but yet farre vnlike that it was before, for now it is reſiſted by the ſpirite, &amp; ſo, either cannot get the members is doe it ſeruice at al, or elſe, if it doe ſo farre prenayle, as to too often it doeth, yet by theforce of the ſpirite they are ſo checked and taken vp for their ſo doing, that neither is there ſuch delighte taken in ſin, as before, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſin after get his will obeyed ſo eaſily again, inſomuch, that thoughe it get his wil now &amp; then done, yet it get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> but with grudging &amp; miſliking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit, &amp; ſo hath neuer ful obedience yéelded it as before, &amp; euery day it obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth leſſe obedience &amp; leſſe. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I may wel compare the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that ſin hath, being in his kingdome, to the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a lawfull &amp; welbeloued King getteth
<pb facs="tcp:2584:15"/>of hys ſubiectes, and the obedience, that ſin only dwelling in man obtaineth, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedience y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a tyrant &amp; vſurper getteth of his ſubiectes that loue him not. Both of theſe get their things that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund done, but in great dinerſitie, for the one is obeyed in all, &amp; that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hartily, &amp; faithfully: the other in as little as they can, &amp; in that repyningly with inwarde griefe &amp; miſliking, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhoulde obey ſuch a one at al: &amp; euen the like difference betwixt obedience, yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him before regeneration and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is there. Take we héed therfore, that ſin raigne not in vs, &amp; wreſtle wée and ſtriue we by the ſpirite euery day more and more to withdrawe our bodies and ſoules from yéelding any obedience to ſin dwelling in vs, and in thus doing, though with Paule we fynd ſome tyme this tyrant letting vs from doing the good we would, and drawing vs on to do the euil that we miſlike, yet with the ſame Paule as wée do take occaſion to crye oute of oure owne wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of the tyranny of ſinne in vs,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:16"/>ſo let vs comfort our ſelues, aſſuring our ſelues that this wreſtling againſt ſinne in the inner man is a ſure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our moſt aſſured purpoſed ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to the end that this doctrine now thus generally layde downe may be to the more comfort of thée Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der particularly, let vs ſée now how it can be applyed to thy fore, to ſalue it: to thy ſickneſſe: to cure it: to thy afflicted conſcience, to ſolace and comfort it: thou mourneſt, and thy ſoule is troubled, deſquieted, and ſore vered within thée, yea, thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe euen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with the paynes of hell, and therfore in bitterneſſe of heart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneſt as one caſt off, forgotten and forſaken of God, fearing greatly that thy ende and portion ſhall be with the wicked: and why is all this? bycauſe ſayeſt thou I find in my ſelfe ſuch doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whether I ſhall be ſaued for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake or no, and many other ſinnes and infirmities in my ſelfe beſide, for the which I deſerue vtterly to be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.
<pb facs="tcp:2584:16"/>But tell me alſo and diſſemble not with me, doeſt thou not greatly miſlike this thy doubting? art thou not gréeued with thy ſelfe for it? findeſt thou not in thy ſelfe an earneſt deſire to be ridde of it, that thou mighteſt fully beléeue that thou ſhalt be ſaued for Chriſtes ſake? and further concerning the other infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, doeſt thou not miſlike them and condemne them in thy ſelfe, and wreſtle and ſtriue to leſſen them in thy ſelfe? and yet to go one ſtep further with theée: doeſt thou not vnfeynedly finde in thy ſelfe loue towards Gods truth, and the profeſſors thereof, euen for that they do profeſſe it and embrace it, and a loue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter godlineſſe, euen for godlineſſe ſake? And that in anſwering of me in theſe two laſt poyntes, you be not deceyued, conſider whether you take any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, pleaſure, and delight in reading of Gods booke, in ſtudying of his truth, in hearing it preached and commoned on, and whether it be a gréefe vnto you to heare it withſtoode or miſliked, or the profeſſors and preachers thereof abuſed,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:17"/>if theſe things be in you, it is certayne you haue loue towardes God and his truth, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bréethren that profeſſe it: and as for loue after godlyneſſe vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally euen for godlyneſſe ſake, then it is in you, if you be at this poynt, that you could finde in your heart to abſteyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, though it might aduantage you, &amp; not hurt you in procuring you here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhame or puniſhment, &amp; to embrace vertue, though it purchaſe you mockes, ſcoffes, and tauntes, and any other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and gayne you nothing wyth menne, euen bycauſe your God hathe condemned the one and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the other. And whether your abſtaynyng from ſinne and embracing of vertue be ſuch as this, you may be able to iudge, if you conſider whither you be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to abſteyne from thoſe ſinnes that man puniſheth not or accounteth not of, as from other: and if you way whether you be not as well willing to embrace thoſe poyntes of godlyneſſe whiche are moſt diſpiſed amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as thoſe that he highlieſt eſtéemed, you can not deny
<pb facs="tcp:2584:17"/>but that to theſe queſtions you muſt néedes anſwer that it is thus with your ſelfe, notwithſtanding your complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of lacke of faith and doubting, that ſometime you haue good comforte in hearing Gods truth in Chriſt Ieſus, and great conſolation in powring forth your Prayers vnto God in the bitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your ſoule: this is it that diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts you, that this comfort of yours la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth but for a ſhort time, your doubting being renued, and yet you can not I am ſure ſay to the contrarye, but that you hope of the renuing of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Chriſt, and of ſaluation through him in the ende. Be it then that this is thy ſtate (Chriſtian Reader) let vs ſée nowe what comfortes the worde of God miniſtreth vnto thée, to binde vp thy broken heart, and to heale thy wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſcience.</p>
            <p>This I dare ſay vnto you by g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d and plentiful experience to begin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in the wordes of Paule <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>10.</hi> verſe <hi>23.</hi> there hath no te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you but ſuch as aperteineth to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and God
<pb facs="tcp:2584:18"/>is faithfull, which will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you be able, but wil giue the iſſue with the temptation, that you may be able to beare it: thus hath he before now oftentimes brought downe to Hell, and carryed backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: he hath throwne downe that hée might rayſe vp: wounded, that he might heale: thus doth he vſe to breake vp the fallow landes of the hearts of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to prepare them as méete ground for the immortal ſéede of his word: thus doth he according to his promiſe Ezech. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. take from his their ſtony heartes, and beſtowes ſoft and fleſhie hearts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them: ſuch a broken and contrite heart as this is, is ſo acceptable a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God, that he will not deſpiſe it, Pſal. <hi>51.</hi> yea to the great conſolation of ſuch, it is ſayd by God Eſay. <hi>66.</hi> verſe. <hi>2.</hi> to him will I looke that is poore, and of a contrite ſpirite, and trembleth at my wordes, and therefore ſo farre off is it that you ſhould be perſwaded that God hath forgotten you or left you off, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the trouble and vexation which
<pb facs="tcp:2584:18"/>you féele in your ſoule, that euen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you haue matter of comfort, aſſuring you that you are one whome moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly he looketh vpon and regardeth. In déede it can not be denyed, but that where there is no faith in Chriſt Ieſus, there is yet the ſtate of damnation, for as it is written, He that beléeueth in him, ſhall not be condemned: ſo it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth writ in the ſame verſe. But hée that beléeueth not, is condemned alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, bycauſe he beléeueth not in the only begotten ſonne of God Ioh. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> verſe. <hi>18.</hi> But your argumente to proue that you haue not faith, neyther yet the fruites, bycauſe you find in your ſelfe the quite contrarie doubting ſinnes and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is not good, for the antecedent may be true, and granted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do ſo doubt, and that there is ſuch ſinnes and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in you, and yet that therefore you are forſaken and caſt off of God, to be denyed: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> making whereof plaine vnto you, you muſt vnderſtand that the life of a Chriſtian is a continuall war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and that this warre is to be found
<pb facs="tcp:2584:19"/>euen in ſuch as Paule was (a man that had faith in greate meaſure, and the fruites thereof) as you haue heard out of the ſeauenth of the Romanes betwixt the inner man and the outwarde, in ſo much that he ſetteth it downe Gala. <hi>5.</hi> verſe <hi>17.</hi> for a certaine point of doctrine, ſaying, the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſhe, and theſe are contrary the one to the other, ſo that ye can not do the ſame things that ye would: whereby we are taught that naturally we are all nothing but the old man, nothing but fleſh both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, and ſuch we remayne by nature the children of wrath Epheſ. <hi>2.</hi> poore captiues in priſon Eſa. <hi>61.</hi> ſold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne Rom. <hi>7.</hi> blind, not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the things of God <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>2.</hi> yea, hauing the beſt thing that is in vs, our wiſedome, a naturall and rebellious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the will of God Rom. <hi>8.</hi> and in this caſe the ſtrong enemie Sathan kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs quietly in his ſubiection, vntill Chriſt Ieſus a ſtronger than he come, &amp; diſpoſſeſſe him, Luke <hi>11.</hi> who entring
<pb facs="tcp:2584:19"/>into poſſeſſion, firſt lightneth our darke hearts with vnderſtanding, and by hys ſpirite worketh faith in vs, and be get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs anew, and ſo we put on the new man, and haue his ſpirite dwelling in vs, Rom. <hi>8.</hi> by which ſpirit we offer bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to the fleſhe, and ſéeke to put off the old man, and to kill &amp; crucifie him with his luſts. But thus the caſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with vs, that we ſhall neuer quite be ridde of this old man, we ſhall neuer fully haue kild and crucifyed the fleſh, vntill death come, for he ſtriketh the laſt blow of the battayle, till then we are in the fielde, and haue continually to ſkirmiſh. Now the ſtate and condition of the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man being thus, and euery one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cauſe to ſay with Paule Rom. <hi>7.</hi> I know that in my fleſh there dwelleth no go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d thing, yea, we vnderſtanding that the fruites of the fleſhe be as the ſame Paule hath told vs, adulterie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, vncleanneſſe, wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, witchcraft, hatered, debate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, wrath, contentions, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hereſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, enui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, murthers, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:20"/>gluttony, and ſuch like, what maruel is it if looking into the fleſh that we carrie vp and downe with vs, we ſée and find therin doubting ſinnes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities? and what ſtrange thing is it then if Sathan our old antient enemie, the more to diſcomforte his aduerſarye the ſpirit but newly come into the field, do cauſe his Lieutenant and Captayne generall of his battell the fleſh, to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter al his power, and to make as great a ſhew of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he can poſſibly? though many of his army in former ſkirmiſhes with the ſpirit haue bin ſore wounded, ſome in the head, ſome in the arme, and ſome one where and ſome another, yet I warrant you, the better and more to daunt his aduerſary and his hoſt, he wil cauſe them vntil they be quite ſlayne, to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in the field: and how is it poſſible but that this Captaine pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his tentes ſo nie vs, but that we hauing eyes to ſée withal, ſhould deſcrie &amp; eſpy his hoſt, &amp; with the greatnes and fierceneſſe thereof in our ſelues he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted at the ſight thereof, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:2584:20"/>as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as we are occupyed rather in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the force bent againſt vs, than the ſtrength of our own Captain Chriſt Ieſus, and his power ready preſent to help &amp; ſuccour vs. I remember that it is written in the ſixt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt of the Kings, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King of <hi>Aram</hi> ſent horſſes and Chareis &amp; a mighty hoſt to take <hi>Eliza</hi> at <hi>Dothan,</hi> and therwith had compaſſed the City where he was by night, his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoſt &amp; their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering only therof, was afraide and ſaid, alas maiſter what ſhal we do: but his maiſter rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoſt that was of his ſide, he anſwered, feare not, for they that be with vs, are mo tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that be with them, and the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts eyes being opened, he perceyned it was ſo, and then his feare was gone. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo we, as long as we are occupyed in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the army of the fleſh &amp; old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we can not but be diſcomforted, but if our eyes were opened, and we woulde be occupyed in beholding &amp; conſidering the ſtrength &amp; force of the new man, &amp; of the ſpirit which is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſide, we ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:2584:21"/>be chéered againe, but be it that the one, and that the fleſh and his hoſt, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, and like to foyle the other: and the other, the ſpirit, neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o yong &amp; weake, and like to be foyled, yet the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit once hauing entred the field, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon the battell, doubt we not, but that in the end he will ouercome the other &amp; his force, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one hath his ſtrength and force but from Sathan a creature, and the other from God the creator, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſure in the end to be the conqueror. <hi>Dauid</hi> in offering and entring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with great <hi>Goliah,</hi> was iudged both of <hi>Saule</hi> and of his aduerſarie farre too weake, but yet in the end he ſlew <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah. 1.</hi> Sam. <hi>17.</hi> for he was the Lordes Champion, and the other but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords enimies y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philiſtins: and therefore be it that the new man in thée be but comparable to little and yong <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the olde man to ſtrong and mightie <hi>Goliah,</hi> yet <hi>Dauid</hi> offering the Combate, let hym putte thee in hope of certayne victorie by hys for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier experience of mightyer conqueſts,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:21"/>as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <hi>Saule,</hi> ſaying: thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant hathe already ſlaine both a Lyon &amp; Beare: my meaning is, in that thou haſt heard and ſéene, that the ſpirit hath ſubdued the fleſh and his power, in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, Mary Magdalene,</hi> and ſnehe like ones, doubt you not but that he ſhall ouercome thy fleſhe neuer yet ſo braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and inured to ſin, as it was in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea, but I heare thy fleſh redy to teach thée to caſt aſide al theſe comfordes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thou haſt not nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot yet this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttel offered or begon in thée, and that therefore theſe things ſal beſide the wel. Yet to beginne withal, thus much is obtayned, if this battell be begonne, that then though looking into the fleſh &amp; the fruits therof, thereby neuer ſo much cauſe be giuen thée to be diſcoraged and diſcomfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that yet looking vppon the ſpirite that reſiſteth and ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, there is ſufficient cauſe of aſſured comforte againe, vnleſſe tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dare ſayd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thinke, that the Diuet can putt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God to flight, &amp; make him altes his purpoſe whiche once to ſurmiſe is blaſphemy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb facs="tcp:2584:22"/>And this is gotten alſo, that in the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man there being as wel fleſhe as ſpirite, the fruites of the fleſhe being as they be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it followeth not, there is in me doubting, and ſins, and infirmities, that deſire. Gods wrath, and therfore I haue no fayth and godlyneſſe accepted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of God in Chriſt Ieſus, for tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughe the former be found in the fleſh, as they haue bin and be in all fleſhe in ſome meaſure, the later is found &amp; may be founde in the newe and inner man, whoſe properties are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the other, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt which faith with diuerſe fruites thereof are reckned Gal. <hi>5.</hi> verſe. <hi>22.</hi> &amp; <hi>23.</hi> thoſe things obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned already, let vs then nowe conſider. whither it be true y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there be in you this battel begun, &amp; that God hath made you a fielde for theſe two might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Captains the ſpirit and the fleſhe to fight a combat togither in. That the one is ther, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fleſh, you graunte: but that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is yet come, the ſpirite you meane, you deny. What do you thinke that any man will fight with himſelfe wil Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:2584:22"/>then thinke you ſtriue againſt himſelfe? if you thinke that it maye ſo be, Chriſtie Luke. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> hath taught you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sathan is wiſer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, taking it for a thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> could not but be granted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sathan would not reſiſt himſelfe, or ſtriue with himſelfe, &amp; therefore proueth the accuſation of bys caſting out of Diuels by the power of Sathan, to be rediculous and fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous, ſaying. If Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be deuided againſt him ſelf, how ſhal hys kingdome ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for as much as you féele in your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues a miſliking of infidelitie or doubting of your ſaluation, a grief for it, &amp; an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to be rid of it, and withal féele a grief for your ſinnes, ioyned with a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of them, and an earneſt deſire to ceaſe from ſinning, I woulde aſke you from whence you thinke all this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, from the ſame fountaine trow you from whence the former, that is the matter of your ſorrow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes? if you thinke ſo, I reply with Iames wordes Cap. <hi>3.</hi> verſe <hi>11.</hi> &amp; <hi>12.</hi> Doth a fountain ſend forth at one place ſwéete water and bitter? can the fig trée bring forth ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes? either a vine figs?
<pb facs="tcp:2584:23"/>yea, wyth Chriſt, Math. <hi>7.</hi> verſe <hi>16.</hi> Do men gather Grapes of Thornes, or figs of thiſtles? Is it poſſible then that theſe things ſhold come from the fleſh where there dwels no good thing, Rom. <hi>7.</hi> Can the blacke Moore change hys ſkynne, or the Leoperd hys ſpottes? Ierem. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22.</hi> then maye this be. Nay theſe be fruites quyte contrary to the fruites of the fleſh as it is well knowen, and therfore they come from the ſpirite: for theſe two and their fruites be contrary the one to the other, Gal. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; therfore, as the fyndyng of &amp; doubting of ſinnes in your ſelfe bée ſure argumentes, that the fleſhe is in the fielde, ſo be theſe as certaine argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſpirit is come, &amp; hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned battel. Further, your confeſſed loue to Gods truth and the profeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, your loue to godlines for it own ſake &amp; miſlike of ſin, not in worldly reſpects, but euen bycauſe it is ſin, youre crying vnto God in your griefe and heauineſſe of ſoule, your comfortes then, and in the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te vſe of the worde, your hope of Gods goodneſſe in the ende towardes you,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:23"/>ſtrengthned by the experience of hys goodneſſe towardes you hitherto, be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo many moſte excellent ſeales and aſſurances vnto you euen from God, that you are his choſen, iuſtified, and ſanctified childe, and that therefore you haue his ſpirite dwelling in you, to war and to ouercom the fleſh to your eternal comfort. O but yet in al this I haue yet no faith. Why ſaiſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſo. Is it not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Rom. <hi>8.</hi> as manye as haue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God be the ſonnes of God? and can anye be the ſoune of God wythoute Faith? therefore, in that thou haſte the ſpirite dwelling in thée, it is certayne thou haſte faith in ſome meaſure. Yea, but I féele it not, but rather the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that in great meaſure: yet being deceyued, thou féeleſt a thing in the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing againſte infidelitie &amp; miſliking it, &amp; that is Faith, for as vertue is reſiſted by his contrary vice, ſo this foule vice of Infidelitie is withſtoode by hys contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vertue which is faith: And it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: how ſhal they pray to him, in whom they haue not beléeued, Rom. <hi>10.14.</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:2584:24"/>then as earneſtly you haue called vpon God in Chriſtes name, ſo manye argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes haue you of faith in hym: And howe coulde you haue had at anye time ſuche comfort in praying, and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the doctrine of the Goſpel, without faith? For, if you haue no faith in Chriſt, then neither hathe hys grace any acceſſe to you to comforte you, nor you to it, thereby to take comforte, for you know, he that is withoute Faith, is withoute Chriſte, and he that is without Chriſte, hath God not his comforter, but his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founder: and therefore thoſe comfortes and conſolations that you haue hadde, muſte remaine wyth you as ſure euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that by Faith you haue Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in you. And thoughe you féele not theſe comfortes ſtill, ſhal you therefore conclude, that you haue no faith? The woman with childe, though ſhe féele not the childe alwayes ſtirre, yet, bicauſe ſhe hath ſometime felt it, ſhe comforteth hir ſelfe, that ſhe is with childe: you knowe ſhe is with childe a good while before ſhe can ſenſibly féele it moue, and at the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:2584:24"/>ſhée féeleth it but weakely, yea, after ſhe hathe felt it ſtrongly, ſome tune ſhe fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it not againe a great whyle, &amp; when ſhe doeth, in muche weakeneſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in compariſon of the former, and yet for all this, hathe in the ende a happy trauell: ſo Faith is not felt to moue ſtrongly as ſoone as it is bred, and when it beginneth once, it continueth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alike motions. It is wyth Faith and withal other the graces of the ſpirit, as it is with the Sunne, which ſometime ſetteth, ſometime ryſeth, ſometime ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, ſometime is couered with cloudes, or ſhadowed from vs by thicke and ſog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gey myſtes ariſing out of the earth: for euen ſo ſometime theſe ſéeme to be ſette and gone downe in vs, but when the morning comes, they ariſe againe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme they are couered from our eyes, by ſuche miſts and cloudes that ariſe out of the fleſhe, that wée cannot eſpye them: but yet for all this, as he reaſoneth ilfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouredly and vntruely, that ſaith, the Sunne cannot be ſéene nowe for clouds, therefore it is not in the firmament: ſo he
<pb facs="tcp:2584:25"/>that ſayeth: I can not ſée and perceiue Faith and the ſpirite in me for the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the fleſhe, therefore they be not in mée. Be not therefore diſcouraged thoughe thou ſynde a Wynter in thy ſelfe ſometime, for if thou haſte hadde once theſe floriſhing fruites of Sommer in thée heretofore, be thou aſſured thou ſhalt haue hereafter a Sommer again, and that the trées and hearbes are not dead, though there appeare and be ſéene little gréeneneſſe in them, for the ſappe remaines in the roote, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, wyll garniſhe all agayne. When thou commeſt into an Orchard, fielde, and Garden, thou canſt comforte thy ſelf with theſe thoughtes: euen doe the like in this: For it is written, that who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loues he loues to the end, Iohn <hi>13.</hi> &amp; in whome he hath begonne thys good worke of Regeneration, in them he wil performe it, Philip. <hi>1.</hi> For the gyfts and calling of God be without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Rom. <hi>11.</hi> And therfore, though they ſéeme to be ſo raked vp &amp; couered wyth aſhes, that they are not ſéene nor
<pb facs="tcp:2584:25"/>perceyued, inſomuch, that Dauid (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king according to his own ſenſe) be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſaye, that God hathe tourned his backe vppon him, and forgotten to bée gratious, &amp; ſhut vp his louing kindneſſe in diſpleaſure, yet in truth it is not ſo, whiche God will make manifeſt in hys good time, by remouing of the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es that couered hys graces and gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes, and by blowing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>les thereof wyth the Bellows of hys ſpirite in the miniſtery of his worde and ſacraments. Further, that hope that is in thée, what is it elſe, but faiths daughter: For when by faith once wée haue learned what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ynges be: prepared for vs at Gods hande in Chriſte Ieſus, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by hope we looke for them in the mid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of moſt grieuous tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tious, wherein Hope playeth a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d daughters p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouriſhing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ngthning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mother, whyche other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then woulde be ready to languiſh: but to hope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings, whiche by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we knowe not before in Chriſte Ieſus to appertayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto vs, in vaine, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>counted in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and
<pb facs="tcp:2584:26"/>that aptlye and worthily, the daughter of Faith, and therefore, in confeſſing that you haue Hope, you confeſſe that you haue Faith alſo: For graunte once, that there is a daughter: and it is alſo of neceſſitie to be graunted, that there was the mother firſt. And whereas thou complayneſt, that thou féeleſt it not, but rather the contrary, I graunt thou neyther féeleſt Faith, nor yet euer ſhall in the fleſhe, but in the inner man. By theſe meanes that I haue ſhewed, thou mayeſt fynde Faith, and therewith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thy ſelfe, and ſaye as the man ſayd to Chriſte: I beléeue Lorde, Lord help my vnbeléete, I beléeue in the ſpirite and inner man, and there I fynde no doubtyng, but a wreſtling againſte the leaſt doubting, and a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iking of it: but in my fleſhe I finde vnbeléefe, whych I beſéeche thée O Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e and helpe. If you dreame (as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ely you do) of ſuche a meaſure of Faith in the ſpirite that ſhoulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yte extinguiſhe, euen the leaſt doubting in the fleſhe, you drea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of that whyche yet neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ll mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2584:26"/>had or ſhall haue, if it be in the ſinner man vnmixte, wyth doubting whych it is: if it miſlike of the leaſt doubting, and ſight againſte it, you haue Faith in his right nature, yea, and the greater your doubting and vnbeléefe in the fleſhe hathe bin, the ſtronger hath your Faith ſhewed it ſelfe, in that notwithſtanding it continueth ſtriuing againſt it, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it &amp; miſliking it: you muſte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the force of Faith in inſtifying dependeth not vpon the quantitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> qualitie, for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Faith, haue not Faith in equall meaſure and quantitie, ſome haue it in ſtrong meaſure, ſome in weak meaſure, but al that by Faith catch holde of their ſaluation, muſt haue like faith in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, they muſte ſéeke their ſaluation at Gods hands in Chriſt Ieſus alone. It is likely you knowe that all thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſralites that looked vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent had not like eyes al in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; clearnes, yet if they had eies, were they neuer ſo little and ſo bleared, yet looking directly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppe, they found helpe
<pb facs="tcp:2584:27"/>as well as the other: Be the beggers hande little or greate, it ſerueth hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to take a penny wythall. So if thou haue a right faith, that is ſuch a faith as ſéeketh and looketh for ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through Chriſt God and man alone, be it that it is but little and weake, yet it ſerueth thy turne. In déede it is god, that fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faith in weake meaſure in vs, we ſhould ſtriue by reading and muſing of the word, by diligent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaring it read and preached, that wée maye growe in faith, and procéed from a weak meaſure of faith to a ſtronger. But yet in anys caſe we muſte take héede, that, hauyng eſcaped from the filthineſſe of Poperie in this point, in ſéeking for any parte of our ſaluation in our owne merites, ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sathan cauſe vs not to ſéeke for our ſaluation, for the worthineſſe of oure faith, which we are very nigh vnto, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are ready to ſaye or thinke, that our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weake faith, though it be neuer ſo right a faith, cannot iuſtifie vs, vnleſſe it were in ſome worthier meaſure. For is not thys a lykelihoode, that wée are about to
<pb facs="tcp:2584:27"/>tye ſaluation to the worthineſſe of faithe Wherefore, to preſerue vs from thys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eight of Sathan, we muſt vnderſtand, that if we accompte it abſurde to ſéeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>luation in worthineſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure other workes, it is as abſurde to tooke for it for the worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of our ſaith: For when wée are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ghte in the worde, that ſaith in the bloude of Chriſte Ieſus iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth, the meaning thereof is not to teache vs that faith hath this four for the toorthineſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſelfe, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of Ieſus Chriſte the obiecte and matter that ſaith findeth out beholdeth and apprehen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. So that the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo much<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icked againſte of the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies of Gods s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> grace, Faith onelye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is that in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>te. Amongeſt al vertues when they are togither, Faith alone hath thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce, though when ſhée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>tes it ſhe be not alone or vnaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auyed of other vertues, to apprehende Chriſte Ieſus, and ſo in him alone to iuſtifie vs: But to retourne againe to your complaint of not féeling faith, and therefore you haue not faith: I muſte
<pb facs="tcp:2584:28"/>tell you further, that I feare in theſe heauenlye thinges you haue folowed to muche ſence and féeling. For, if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> woulde iudge aright whether you haue faith or no, and whether you be Gods déere chylde or no, you muſte not iudge by ſence and féeling, but by the words of Almightie God. So that if your ſence and féeling leade you one way to iudge of your ſelfe, and the word of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and you an other waye, you muſte pref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the iudgemente and determination, of God in hys worde, who knowes bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe thinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ée o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſelues, who is better to bée beléeued than our owns ſence and féeling, before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of fleſhe and blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. To refuſe thus to doe, is to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>then to beléeue oure ſelues than GOD, and to preſume, that we by oure owne ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; féeling can iudge better in what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, we ſtande, than GOD hymſelfe that made vs, whyche is greate blaſphemy. Wherefore, to lette goe talking of youre owne ſence and féeling, if you
<pb facs="tcp:2584:28"/>be deſtrous to know your eſtate, would you haue a better and ſurer Iudge than God himſelfe to tell you it? In déede ſays you, if hée woulde come downe from Heauen, and tell me, I ſhould then I hope beléeue hym. Euen ſo he hathe in hys worde: and if an Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from Heauen ſhoulde come and tell you otherwiſe than in his worde he hathe tolde you, you haue Paules war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to holde him accurſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I hope you wil hold that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that féeling, that reaſon, that perſon, &amp; that Diuel accurſed, that dare be ſo bold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reafter, as to tell you otherwiſe of your ſelfe and your eſtate than GOD hymſelfe hathe pronounced in this hys worde. Hearken therefore wyth a mind readye to yéelde your ſubſcription vnto Gods iudgement in hys worde.</p>
            <p>We are tolde, Eſay <hi>61.</hi> that Chriſte was annoynted, bycauſe the ſpirite of God was vpon him, to preach glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings vnto the pore, to bind vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearted, to preache libertie to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and to them that are bound, the
<pb facs="tcp:2584:29"/>opening of the priſon to preache the acceptable yeare of the Lords, and the daye of vengeance of our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte all that mourne, to appoynt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that mourne in <hi>Syon,</hi> and to giue vnto them beautie for aſhes, the oyle of ioye for mourning, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of gladneſſe for the ſpirite of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe, that they myghte bée cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Trées of Righteouſneſſe, the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Lorde, that he myghts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glorified: whereby wée learne, that thoſe Chriſte hathe cured and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that bée trées of Ryghteouſneſſe of the Lordes plantyng, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is glorified. Nowe Iohn <hi>15.</hi> wée learne that thoſe trées of Ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that bee of the Lordes planting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they bée planted and grafted into Chriſt Ieſus, and there alſo we are taughte as the branch cannot heare fruit of it ſelfe, excepte it abide in the Vine, no more can wée excepte wée abyde in Chriſte.</p>
            <p>In theſe twoo places then this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is flatlye taughte vs, that wée can not bee good trées of Ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2584:29"/>wherevpon good fruite is found gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing, vnleſſe we be ſuch as be enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, fréed, deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed, cured, and healed by Chriſt, yea vntill we be ſuch as both be ingrafted into Chriſt, and childe in him. Now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they that be in this caſe be elected and iuſtified, hane faith, be the children and ſonnes of God in the ende to be glorified, you can not denie; now then, looke vpon your wreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing againſt infidelitie and other ſinnes, your loue towards God and his truth, and to all godlyneſſe vnſeypedly, and you ſhall ſinne that not only the matter of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> found in hipocrites, but the matter done in right maner, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules before ſet downe, be founde in you, what betteth then, but that according to Saint Peters counſel you ſhould accompt your election ſure, and that you ſhall neuer fall. <hi>1.</hi> Peter. <hi>2.</hi> Theſe things you know, that doing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rie to the ſpirite of God that hathe wrought them in you, you can not deny but that they are good fruites of fayth; and of one iuſtified thereby: and then ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2584:30"/>you are enforced to conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe that theſe be in you, vnleſſe you would<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cleane contrarie to Chriſtes indgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſay Math. <hi>7.</hi> that an yll trée can bring foorth good fruite, confeſſe that you are in the ſight of God a good trée, as the Lorde hath made it manifeſt to you to your comfort, by cauſing theſe fruites to grow on you. To come to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, you know Chriſt hath ſayde, Lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one another as I haue loued you, that is, as Iohn expoundes it, in déede an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſtle Chap. <hi>3.</hi> and by this ſhall all men knowe that you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſciples, whiche leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n was of that force with Iohn, that finding in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe loue towardes the bréethren, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſte, he ſet downe this po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hymſelfe, and of all ſuche. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowe that we are tranſlated from death vnto life, bycauſe we loue the bréethren <hi>1.</hi> Iohn. <hi>2.</hi> verſe <hi>14.</hi> Marke he ſayeth, we know, not we thinke or ſuppoſe, thereby teaching vs to accompt thys fruite founde in vs an infallible argumente of oure bleſſed eſtate. And
<pb facs="tcp:2584:30"/>in the nexte Chapter hée teacheth vs to knowe whether we bée ledde by the ſpirite of truth or errour, by oure willingneſſe to heare the faithfull mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, ſaying: He that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth God heareth vs, he that is not of God heareth vs not, héereby knowe we the ſpirite of errour and the ſpirite of truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and a little after he addeth, and héereby knowe we that we dwell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hym, and he in vs, bycauſe he hathe gyuen vs of hys ſpirit. Thus then you in the iudgement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the word is, that you are a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> tree of the Lordes plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aning, abiding in Chriſt Ieſus, that you are one of Chriſtes Diſciples, tranſlated from deathe to life, and ledde by the ſpirite of truth, and therefore ſuche an one as dwelles in the fauour of God; this is Gods ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and iudgement of you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thankefully prayſe him, and bring once all your thoughtes and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ſet vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt this, into obedience herevnto: quench not
<pb facs="tcp:2584:31"/>the ſpirit, neyther yet gréeue any longer the ſpirite of grace,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 19. Ephe. 4.30.</note> whereby you are thus comfortably ſealed vnto the day of redemption, be no longer vnthankefull vnto God in ſtaying from confeſſing your ſelfe to be his childe, and to haue faith. Be of good cheere, the Lorde hath giuen you beautie for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rning, the garment of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the ſpirite of heauineſſe, and therefore ſay with the Prophet in the ſame place Eſay. <hi>61.</hi> I will greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the Lord, and we ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God, for he hath clothed me with the garments of ſaluation, and couered me with the robe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea, he hath decked me like a Bridegrome, and as a Bride tireth hir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe with iewels: and let not yours weakeneſſe and bruſedneſſe any wore diſmay you, for you haue a God that will not quench the ſmoking ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are, not yet breake the bruſed réede. Neyther yet let the chaunges and alterations that you find in your ſelfe diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t you, for God is no changeling neyther in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:2584:31"/>nor in his giftes Mal. <hi>3.</hi> Iames. <hi>1.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om. <hi>11.</hi> and though Sathan be bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e in making warre, and in renewing his aſſaults, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt not, if you were not Gods childe, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he néeded not, neyther yet would ſo ſtriue with you, he warreth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that be his, but is at peace with them, and Chriſt that hath taken in hande the kéeping of you, is a good Shepeheard, and hath triumphed ouer ſinne, and ouercome him, and therefore he is bold to ſay Iohn. <hi>10.</hi> My Shéepe ſhall neuer periſh, neyther ſhall anye plucke them out of my hands Pſal. <hi>28.</hi> if we by the force of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie be cauſed to ſtray ſometime, yet he giueth vs not ouer, but ſéeketh vs till he finde vs, and then he layeth vs on his ſhoulder, and bringeth vs home againe Luke. <hi>15.</hi> and therefore let vs euen boldly truſt our ſelues with him, nothing doubting, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if he leade vs at any time into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he wil ſtand by vs, and ſo preſerue vs, that we ſhal happily get out again, to his glory and our comforte, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:2584:32"/>God the Father graunt vs, euen for this hys ſonnes ſake, now and euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. To which God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons and one true and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer liuing God, be all prayſe, honor and dominion for euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2584:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
